{"tossups": [{"question": "This alchemist and pursuer of the philosopher's stone developed a theory of color he discussed in the book<em> Opticks</em>. This scientist's<em> Mathematical Principles of Natural Philosophy</em> explained his law of universal gravitation, developed using a calculus notation he derived independently of Gottfried Leibniz [[LIBE-nitz]]. For ten points, name this English polymath who also theorized three eponymous laws of motion.", "answer": "Sir Isaac <b><u>Newton</u></b>", "metadata": "Philosophy - Philosophy"}, {"question": "In 1903, President Theodore Roosevelt set aside this island's Crown Lands of El Yunque [[YOON-keh]] to establish a forest reserve, and today, that region of this island is the only tropical U.S National Forest. The Arecibo [[ah-reh-SEE-boh]] Observatory, a radio telescope on this island, collapsed in late 2020. This island's capital city of San Juan is the oldest European settlement in what is now the United States. For ten points, name this Spanish-speaking island, the largest U.S. commonwealth.", "answer": "Commonwealth of <b><u>Puerto Rico</u></b> (or Estado Libre Asociado de <b><u>Puerto Rico</u></b>; accept <b><u>Boriken</u></b>)", "metadata": "Geography - Geography"}, {"question": "In the<em> Life of Saint Boniface</em>, the title saint cuts down a tree sacred to this non-Roman deity in Hesse [[HEH-suh]]. In his treatise<em> Germania</em>, Tacitus [[TASS-ih-tuss]] referred to this god as the \"Hercules\" of the Suebi [[SWAY-bee]] people, while \"Mercury\" was the equivalent of Odin. In opposition to the Christianization of Scandinavia, many believers wore charms depicting this god's hammer Mj\u00f6lnir [[MYOHL-neer]]. For ten points, name this widely-worshipped red-headed Norse god of thunder.", "answer": "<b><u>Thor</u></b> (accept <b><u>Thunar</u></b>; or <b><u>Donar</u></b>)", "metadata": "Mythology - Mythology"}, {"question": "The idea for this work's fourth and final movement was likely borrowed from the work of Luigi Cherubini [[keh-roo-BEE-nee]] and consists of a lengthy coda followed by 29 bars of C Major chords. This piece's composer supposedly told his secretary, Anton Schindler, that its opening motif represented \"fate knocking at the door.\" A famous \"short-short-short-long\" motif opens, for ten points, what symphony by Ludwig von Beethoven?", "answer": "Beethoven's <b><u>Fifth</u></b> (or Symphony No. <b><u>5</u></b> by Ludwig van Beethoven in C minor)", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Auditory Fine Arts"}, {}, {"question": "Josef Stalin sent employees of this company\u2019s<em> Gorki</em> plant in Nizhny Novgorod to a gulag during the Great Purge. In 1932, more than 60 workers were injured by this company's security and Dearborn police following [this company's] \"Hunger March.\" This company\u2019s \u201cEdsel\u201d line of cars was named for the son of its founder and became synonymous with failure in the 1950s. For ten points, name this company which made the popular Escort, F-Series, and Model T automobiles.", "answer": "<b><u>Ford</u></b> Motor Company", "metadata": "Current Events - Current Events"}, {"question": "John Balliol [[BAY-lee-ahl]] abdicated this position and was successfully freed by Pope Boniface VIII [[the eighth]] following Edward I's invasion of his kingdom. One of Idi Amin's many titles proclaimed him to be the \"Last\" person to hold this regal position. The Catholic-driven \"Rising of the North\" attempted to replace Elizabeth I with her cousin Mary, who held this title. Robert the Bruce and the House of Stuart held, for ten points, what royal title also held by Macbeth?", "answer": "<b><u>Ruler</u></b> of <b><u>Scotland</u></b> (or <b><u>Ruler</u></b> of <b><u>Scots</u></b>; accept \"Monarch\", \"Queen\", or \"King\" in place of \"Ruler\")", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "Several city-states of this civilization were defeated by their rival, Spearthrower Owl, a leader of Teotihuacan [[teh-oh-tee-HWAH-kan]]. The military outpost of Dos Pilas [[PEE-lahss]] switched between this civilization's two rival cities of Calakmul [[kah-lahk-MOOL]] and Tikal [[tee-KAHL]]. The Temple of Kukulcan [[koo-kool-KAHN]] was built in this civilization's settlement of Chichen Itza [[CHEE-chen EE-tzah]]. For ten points, name these Mesoamerican people who developed a namesake \"Long Count\" calendar.", "answer": "<b><u>Maya</u></b> People (or <b><u>Maya</u></b>ns; accept <b><u>K'iche</u></b> people)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "Chemist Friedrich Accum [[ah-KUHM]] wrote a treatise concerning this food, denouncing the pre-modern practice of using non-foods such as chalk and sawdust as additives. The scarcity of this foodstuff led to the \"March on Versailles\" [[vehr-\"SIGH\"]] by Parisian women in the early French Revolution. In Juvenal's [[JOO-veh-nahls]]<em> Satires</em>, he paired this word with \"circuses\" to signify mollifying the masses. For ten points, name this staple food of the Western world made from grinding and baking wheat.", "answer": "<b><u>Bread</u></b> (accept <b><u>Pan</u></b>em; accept specific types of <b><u>Bread</u></b>; prompt on \"Grain\")", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {"question": "This case, whose majority opinion cited<em> Federalist Papers</em> No. 78, began as a result of James Markham Marshall failing to deliver commissions prior to a presidential inauguration. This case concerned the appointment of \"midnight judges\" at the tail end of the administration of John Adams. The principle of \"Judicial Review\" was established by, for ten points, what 1803 case, the first major decision by the Marshall court?", "answer": "<em><b><u>Marbury</u></b> v. Madison</em> (or<em> William</em> <em><b><u>Marbury</u></b> v. James Madison, Secretary of State of</em> <em>the United States</em>)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "During this war, the burning lights of trailing hospital ships triggered the Battle of Tsushima [[soo-SHE-mah]] Strait, a disastrous loss for the 2nd Pacific Squadron. Teddy Roosevelt earned a Nobel Peace Prize for negotiating the Treaty of Portsmouth, which ended this conflict. The Battle of Port Arthur began, for ten points, what war in which Emperor Meiji's [[MAY-jees]] government attempted to curb the influence of a tsarist empire?", "answer": "<b><u>Russo-Japanese</u></b> War (accept <b><u>Russko-yaponskaya</u></b> Voyna; or <b><u>Nichiro senso</u></b>)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {}, {"question": "While serving under this general, Dubliner Arthur Sandes led a critical charge of riflemen during the Battle of Boyac\u00e1 [[boh-yah-KAH]]. A series of massacres committed by Royalists led this general to call for the \"Decree of War to the Death\" during the Admirable Campaign. This military commander served as the autocrat of Gran Colombia until his deposition in 1830. For ten points, name this Latin American \"liberator.\"", "answer": "Sim\u00f3n <b><u>Bol\u00edvar</u></b>", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {}, {}, {}, {"question": "Often incorporating aspects of the cult of Serapis [[seh-RAP-iss]], this deity names a \"Mystery\" practiced in the Greco-Roman world which guaranteed practitioners a place in the Fortunate Isles. An aspect of this goddess related to \"Pharos\" [[FAY-rohss]] was worshipped by sailor's hoping to have favorable seas. Scholars have speculated that images of this goddess with Horus on her lap inspired iconography of Mary with an infant Christ. Osiris [[oh-\"SIGH\"-riss]] is resurrected by, for ten points, which sister-wife of his, an Egyptian fertility deity?", "answer": "<b><u>Isis</u></b> [[\"EYE\"-siss]] (accept <b><u>Isis</u></b> Pelagia; accept <b><u>Ese</u></b>; accept <b><u>Wusa</u></b>)", "metadata": "Mythology - Mythology"}, {}, {"question": "Amelia Bloomer and Martha Coffin Wright attended this meeting, at which the Declaration of Sentiments was drafted. Frederick Douglass, the only Black person to attend this event, argued to push for the right to vote. This event's occurrence coincided with a visit to the namesake town by James and Lucretia Mott. For ten points, name this 1848 convention organized by Elizabeth Cady Stanton to discuss women's rights.", "answer": "<b><u>Seneca Falls</u></b> Convention", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {}, {}, {"question": "This ruler's namesake \"Donation\" was a forged 8th century decree claiming he made Rome superior to the other Holy Sees, such as Antioch. This ruler ordered the symbol<em> Chi</em> <em>Rho</em> [[KYE ROE]] to be painted on his soldiers' shields to assure victory at Milvian Bridge. This ruler ended the systemic persecution of Christians through the Edict of Milan. The Council of Nicaea [[ny-SAY-ah]] was called by, for ten points, which \"Great\" Roman emperor who created a namesake capital from the city of Byzantium?", "answer": "<b><u>Constantine</u></b> I (or <b><u>Constantine</u></b> the Great; accept Flavius Valerius <b><u>Constantinus</u></b>; or <b><u>Konstantinos</u></b>)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {"question": "<b><u>Following the Battle of Niagara Falls, one side in this war ceased attempts to</u> <u>conquer Canada. One side in this war lost the Battle of the Thames [[TEMZ]] after (+)</u> recruiting Tecumseh's Confederacy. The Treaty of Ghent officially ended this war shortly before Andrew Jackson's forces won the Battle of New Orleans. (*)</b> For ten points, name this early-nineteenth century conflict that rekindled animosity between Great Britain and the United States.", "answer": "War of <b><u>1812</u></b> (prompt on \"Sixty Years' War\")", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "<b><u>In the prelude to this battle, one side scored easy victories at Bordeaux</u> <u>[[bor-DOE]] and Narbonne over Duke Odo the Great. During this battle, many</u> <u>Mozarabic soldiers abandoned the general Abd al-Rahman in (+)</u> an effort to protect their own camp from being plundered. Prior to this battle, Pope Gregory III provided a loan to a \"Mayor of the Palace\" nicknamed \"The Hammer\" to repel an Umayyad (*) </b>invasion of Gaul. For ten points, name this 732 Frankish victory by Charles Martel.", "answer": "Battle of <b><u>Tours</u></b> (accept Battle of <b><u>Poitiers</u></b>)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "<b><u>A raid against this man's village of Bedonkohe [[bee-don-KO-heh]] by Jose</u> <u>Maria Carrasco led to his lifelong hatred of the Mexican army. This \"Tiger of the</u> <u>Human Race\" spent the last 23 years of his life in captivity following his surrender to</u> <u>Nelson Miles in Skeleton (+)</u> Canyon. Paratroopers during the Second World War popularized shouting this chief's name before jumping out of a plane. (*)</b> For ten points, name this 19th century Apache chief.", "answer": "<b><u>Geronimo</u></b> (accept <b><u>Goyaal\u00e9</u></b>)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "<b><u>Cuban poet Jos\u00e9 Mart\u00ed wrote a</u></b><em><b><u> Centenario</u></b></em><b><u> of this man in 1889, calling him a</u> <u>\"Hero in Peace and War.\" Phillis Wheatley (+)</u> wrote, \"Proceed, great chief, with virtue on thy side\" in an 18th-century poem titled for this politician. Parson Weems composed many stories about this man, including the fable of his chopping down a (*) </b>cherry tree. For ten points, name this literature-inspiring first president of the United States.", "answer": "George <b><u>Washington</u></b> (accept \"To His Excellency, General <b><u>Washington</u></b>\")", "metadata": "Literature - American Literature - Poetry"}, {"question": "<b><u>Due to using this network, John van Zandt was taken to court for punitive</u> <u>damages by plantation owner Wharton Jones. \"Conductors\" who used this network</u> <u>used \"stations\" as (+)</u> safehouses often run by members of the Quaker denomination including Levi Coffin. The nickname \"Moses\" was given to this entity's most successful guide, Harriet Tubman. (*)</b> For ten points, name this so-called \"railroad,\" a series of routes used by the enslaved to escape to the Northern U.S. and Canada.", "answer": "<b><u>Underground</u></b> Railroad", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "<b><u>In an attempt to end this war, a cohort of wives threatens to withhold romance</u> <u>from their men in the play</u></b><em><b><u> Lysistrata</u></b></em><b><u>. The Aristophanes [[\"air\"-ih-STAH-feh-nees]]</u> <u>play</u></b><em><b><u> Peace</u></b></em><b><u> celebrated the recently-signed Peace of Nicias [[nee-KEE-us]] meant (+)</u> to halt this war for fifty years. During this war, the statesman Pericles [[PEH-rih-klees]] gave a funeral oration at a cemetery near the Acropolis. The contemporary Thucydides [[thoo-SIH-dih-dees]] wrote a</b><em><b> History of</b></em><b>, (*)</b> for ten points, what Greek conflict between two factions led by Athens and Sparta?", "answer": "<b><u>Peloponnesian</u></b> War", "metadata": "History - Ancient History"}, {"question": "<b><u>This anti-imperialist openly criticized the U.S. for perpetrating the Moro</u> <u>Crater Massacre in his essay</u></b><em><b><u> Incident in the Philippines</u></b></em><b><u>. This Southerner served a</u> <u>two-week stint in a Confederate militia known as the (+)</u> Marion Rangers before deserting. This Missouri man described his time as a steamboat pilot in the antebellum period in</b><em><b> Life of on the</b></em><b> (*)</b><em> Mississippi</em>. For ten points, name this writer whose Southern upbringing inspired<em> The Adventures of Huckleberry Finn</em>.", "answer": "Mark <b><u>Twain</u></b> (or Samuel Langhorne <b><u>Clemens</u></b>)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "<b><u>This U.S. president admitted the United States's only pair of twin-born states</u> <u>after shuffling their papers to conceal which was the first admitted. The final state</u> <u>this president admitted, out of six, was the first to grant (+)</u> women the vote as a territory. This president presided over the \"Billion Dollar Congress\" and signed the Sherman Antitrust (*)</b> Act. For ten points, name this man who was both successor and predecessor of Grover Cleveland.", "answer": "<b><u>B</u></b>enjamin <b><u>Harrison</u></b> (prompt on \"Harrison\")", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}], "bonuses": []}